<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../../../frameworks/tei-custom/css/all.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Ontologies, Data Modeling, and TEI</title>
        <author>
          <name><forename>Øyvind</forename>
            <surname>Eide</surname></name>
          <affiliation>Øyvind Eide holds a PhD in Digital Humanities from King’s College London
            (2013) and is one of the two founding conveners of the TEI Ontologies SIG. His research
            interests are focused on the modeling of cultural heritage information, especially as a
            tool for critical engagement with the relationships between texts and maps as media of
            communication. He is a <roleName>lecturer</roleName> and <roleName>research
              associate</roleName> at the Chair of Digital Humanities, <orgName>University of
              Passau</orgName>, Germany.</affiliation>
          <email>oyvind.eide@uni-passau.de</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
        <date>2015</date>
        <availability>
          <p>TEI Consortium 2015 (Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License)</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
        <editor role="guest">Arianna Ciula</editor>
        <editor role="guest">Fabio Ciotti</editor>
        <editor role="chief">John Walsh</editor>
        <editor role="managing">Martin Holmes</editor>
        <editor role="technical">Ron Van den Branden</editor>
        <biblScope unit="issue" n="8">Selected Papers from the 2013 TEI Conference</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source, born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in the
          humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish full-text
          articles online.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">en</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords xml:lang="en">
          <term>ontologies</term>
          <term>conceptual modeling</term>
          <term>interchange</term>
          <term>CIDOC-CRM</term>
          <term>linked data</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div type="abstract">
        <p>This paper discusses the relationships between TEI and ontologies from the perspective of
          computer-based modeling, understood here as a way to establish meaning. The distinctions
          between creation and use of models as well as between modeling for production and modeling
          for understanding are presented and compared with other categorizations or models of
          modeling. One method of establishing meaning in TEI documents is achieved via linking
          mechanisms between TEI and external ontologies. How such linking can be done and what it
          may imply for the semantic openness and usability of TEI documents is the practical focus
          of this article.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="intro">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>In philosophy, <term>ontology</term> has for at least 2,500 years denoted the study of
          being. Computer science <term>ontologies</term>, usually in the plural, are different from
          the philosophical concept of ontology. Computer science ontologies refer to shared
          conceptualizations expressed in formal languages (<ref type="bibl" target="#gruber09"
            >Gruber 2009</ref>) and have been a topic of study for some thirty years, initially
          connected to the artificial intelligence community. They have not been of much importance
          in digital humanities until the last ten to fifteen years, but are now gaining momentum as
          the semantic web develops.</p>
        <p>In this paper I will discuss ontologies in the context of the Text Encoding Initiative
          and based on the computer science tradition.<note>This paper springs out of work in the
            TEI Ontologies SIG since 2004. It is also based on long discussions with colleagues at
            the Unit for Digital Documentation at the University of Oslo and beyond. Two anonymous
            reviewers of this article and the editors of the journal contributed significantly to
            its final form. However, the interpretation and formulation, and responsibility for its
            errors and omissions, is mine alone.</note> However, although computer science
          ontologies are different from philosophical ontology, the two are not totally disconnected
            (<ref type="bibl" target="#zuniga01">Zúñiga 2001</ref>), and therefore some remarks will
          be made on relations with philosophy as well. The focus will be on how meaning can be
          established in computer-based modeling. Three broad areas will be
          <?oxy_insert_start author="Cristian Talau" timestamp="20151123T155003+0200"?>as<?oxy_insert_end?>described.
          One is the establishment of meaning through working with and interpreting documents seen
          as sources for scholarly work, be they primary or secondary. Another area is the
          establishment of meaning through the development of models, including ontologies. A third
          area of meaning production with particular reference to TEI happens through linking
          between TEI documents and external ontologies. How such linking can be done and what it
          may imply for the meaning and usability of TEI documents is an important focus of this
          article.</p>
        <p>TEI represents a shared conceptualization of what exists in the domains relevant to text
          encoding. It can be expressed in formal models, but it is questionable whether TEI can be
          seen as an ontology in the computer science sense. According to the classification by
          Guarino, Oberle, and Staab (<ref type="bibl" target="#guarino09">2009, 12–13</ref>), XML
          schemas are typically not expressive enough for the formality we need for ontologies.
          However, the level of language formality forms a continuum, and it is difficult to draw a
          strict line where the formal starts. So for instance, some parts of the TEI scheme, such
          as the systems used to encode dictionaries, bibliographies, and representations of
          persons, places, and events, may be closer to an ontology than other, less formalized
          parts of the standard (<ref type="bibl" target="#ore09">Ore and Eide 2009</ref>).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
